Guide to the Sam Shepard Papers
The Wittliff Collections
Sam Shepard Papers
1980-1999
The Wittliff Collections
Shepard, Sam, 1943-2017
SWWC.054
13 Linear Feet
27 boxes
The Sam Shepard Papers document the middle years of Sam Shepard's literary and acting career, from 1980-1999. The collection is comprised of the following series: Plays, Novels, Short Stories, Films, Literary Criticism, Notebooks, Correspondence, Clippings, Awards, Interviews, Readings, Published Compilations, Works by Others, and Framed Posters.
Conditions Governing Access
Some materials restricted. Please contact the Wittliff Collections for information about access.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Sam Shepard, 1992-2000.
Related Materials
The Wittliff Collection also holds the Sam Shepard and Johnny Dark Collection (SWWC Collection 106).
The Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center at the University of Texas at Austin houses additional Sam Shepard Papers.
Biographical or Historical Information
Widely considered one of America's greatest living playwrights, Sam Shepard is also an accomplished actor, director, screenwriter, and musician. Born Samuel Shepard Rogers IV on November 5, 1943 in Fort Sheridan, Illinois, Shepard is the oldest of three children. His family traveled extensively before settling in Duarte, California, outside of Pasadena, where his childhood experiences informed themes that mark much of his later playwriting. Shepard described Duarte as a "weird accumulation of things, a strange kind of melting pot – Spanish, Okie, Black, Midwestern elements all jumbled together. People on the move who couldn't move anymore, who wound up in trailer parks." (Rolling Stone, 1986). Shepard told biographer Don Shewey that his alcoholic father "had a real short fuse," and that he was often the target of his father's anger. In high school he began acting and writing poetry. He also worked as a stable hand at a horse ranch in Chino, California from 1958-1960. Thinking of becoming a veterinarian, Shepard studied agriculture at Mount Antonio Junior College for a year; but when a traveling theater group, The Bishop's Company Repertory Players, came through town, Shepard joined them and left home. After touring with them from 1962-1963, he moved to New York City and worked as a bus boy at the Village Gate in Greenwich Village.
In New York, Shepard spent much of his time reading the works of playwrights and writing short "rock and roll" plays which frequently focused "on a single event, the characters often talking past one another or breaking into long monologues. However puzzling the action, these plays already ring out with Shepard's deft rhythms," (Contemporary Dramatists 1999). Shepard disavowed the narrative convention that required consistent character motivations, preferring instead to see his characters as capable of a wide variety of roles and actions. Shepard once told an interviewer that, "I preferred a character that was constantly unidentifiable, shifting through the actor, so that the actor could play almost anything, and the audience was never expected to identify with the characters," (Shewey, Sam Shepard, 1997, p. 51). Shepard reconsidered this initial approach to his writing as a result of the influence of New York director and acting teacher Joseph Chaikin. As Shepard said, Chaikin helped him understand that there's, "…no room for self indulgence in theater; you have to be thinking about the audience." (Kevin Berger, salon.com, January 2, 2001) Chaikin also convinced Shepard to begin re-writing his plays in order to discover the essence of the experience. Prior to that, Shepard said, his "tendency was to jam, like it was jazz or something." (Berger, salon.com, January 2, 2001)
Shepard's playwriting debut took place at Theater Genesis on October 16, 1964, with a double bill of Cowboys and Rock Garden. In 1966, he received a grant from the University of Minnesota, the first of several he would receive in the coming years. Also in 1966, he won an unprecedented trio of Obie awards for Chicago, Icarus' Mother, and Red Cross. The awards, presented by off-off Broadway champion The Village Voice, helped Shepard's career gain momentum at a time when critics remained wary of his works.
In 1967, Shepard wrote La Turista, his first full-length play, which won an Obie the same year. More Obies for his early works followed, including Melodrama Play and Cowboys #2 in 1968. Shepard also received grants from the Rockefeller Foundation in 1967 and the Guggenheim Foundation in 1968. Also in 1968, Shepard joined a rock band, the Holy Modal Rounders, playing drums and guitar. Although he played with the band for three years, he continued to write and received a second Guggenheim Foundation grant in 1971.
Shepard married O-Lan Jones Dark, an actress, on November 9, 1969, with whom he had one son, Jesse Mojo Shepard. Shepard and Dark divorced in 1984. In 1971, Shepard had a much-publicized relationship with rock singer Patti Smith. Together they wrote Cowboy Mouth, acting the parts on stage in the first night's performance.
In 1971, Shepard and family traveled to England, where four more plays premiered (The Tooth of Crime, Blue Bitch, Geography of a Horse Dreamer, and Little Ocean). Tooth of Crime was later presented in the U.S., winning an Obie in 1973. The next year, Shepard returned to the United States and served as the playwright in residence for The Magic Theater in San Francisco, a post he held for the next ten years. It was during this time that Shepard made his mark on mainstream American drama, winning the Pulitzer Prize for Drama in 1979 for his play Buried Child and producing his best-known plays, among them, True West in 1980.
In 1975, he took part in Bob Dylan's "Rolling Thunder Review," a nationwide touring group that included Joan Baez, Joni Mitchell, Allen Ginsberg, and William Burroughs. Shepard eventually published an account of the experience in 1987, titled Rolling Thunder Logbook. In 1978, Shepard began his film career, appearing in Bob Dylan's Renaldo and Clara and later that year in Days of Heaven, directed by Terence Mallick. Also in 1978, Shepard began his collaboration with Joseph Chaikin, with the theater piece, Tongues. Chaikin and Shepard would also collaborate on Savage/Love (1979), and The War in Heaven, which was presented on WBAI radio in 1985.
In the 1980s, his works continued to win awards. He won his eleventh Obie for Fool for Love (1984.) A Lie of the Mind won the New York Drama Critics Award in 1986. Also during the 1980s, Shepard's screenwriting and acting career began to grow. Screenplays included Me and My Brother, Zabriskie Point, and Fool for Love. His most popular and critically acclaimed film, Paris, Texas, won a Golden Palm Awards at the Cannes Film Festival in 1984. This screenplay was commissioned by German director Wim Wenders, and was based loosely on Shepard's Motel Chronicles. His acting roles included Resurrection (1980), Raggedy Man (1981), Frances (1982), The Right Stuff (1983), for which he received an Academy Award nomination, Country (1984), Fool for Love (1985), Crimes of the Heart (1986), and Steel Magnolias (1989). He wrote and directed Far North (1988), which starred Jessica Lange.
Shepard continued to write new plays in the 1990s, though his output has slowed from the dizzying pace of the 1960s-1970s. States of Shock premiered in 1991, and in 1992 a revised version of True West was nominated for a Tony Award for Best Drama. Simpatico opened in 1994, and his revision of Buried Child opened on Broadway in 1996 and received a Tony Award nomination. Another collaboration with Joseph Chaikin, When the World Was Green (A Chef's Fable) also premiered in 1996.
Shepard's collection of stories, Cruising Paradise, was published by Knopf in 1996. Curse of the Starving Class opened in 1997 and Eyes for Consuela (based on an Octavio Paz short story) was produced in 1998. In 2001, Shepard returned to San Francisco's The Magic Theater for the premier of his new play The Late Henry Moss.
Shepard's acting career also flourished through the 1990s and 2000s, with appearances in Defenseless (1991), Thunderheart (1992), The Pelican Brief (1993), and The Good Old Boys (1995), among others. Shepard wrote and directed the feature film Silent Tongue (1992). Some of his additional film appearances include All the Pretty Horses (2000), based on the novel of the same name by Cormac McCarthy, Blackhawk Down (2001), Swordfish (2001), The Notebook (2004), Stealth (2005), Walker (2005), and Bandidas (2006).
Shepard was inducted into the American Academy of Arts and Letter in 1986. In 1992, he received the Gold Medal for Drama from the Academy and in 1994 he was inducted into the Theater Hall of Fame. From 1983 to 2010, Shepard was in a committed relationship with actress Jessica Lange, with whom has two children, Hannah Jane Shepard and Samuel Walker Shepard.
Shepard's impact on modern theater can be gauged by the numerous scholarly books and articles devoted to his work, as well as the hundreds of productions of his plays, both in the U.S. and abroad.
Further readings:
American Dreams: The Imagination of Sam Shepard. Edited by Bonnie Marranca. New York: Performing Arts Journal Publications, 1981.
Auerbach, Doris. Sam Shepard, Arthur Kopit, and the Off Broadway Theater. Boston: Twayne, 1982.
Mottram, Ron. Inner Landscapes: The Theater of Sam Shepard. Columbia: Univ. of Missouri Press, 1984.
Shewey, Don. Sam Shepard. New York: Dell, 1985.
Patraka, Vivian M., and Siegel, Mark. Sam Shepard. Boise, Idaho: Boise State University, 1985.
Oumano, Ellen. Sam Shepard: The Life and Work of an American Dreamer. New York: St. Martin's Press, 1986; London: Virgin, 1987.
Hart, Lynda. Sam Shepard's Metaphorical Stages. Westport, Conn.: Greenwood Press, 1987.
King, Kimball. Sam Shepard: A Casebook. New York: Garland, 1988.
Trussler, Simon, ed. File on Shepard. London: Methuen, 1989.
DeRose, David J. Sam Shepard. New York: Twayne, 1992.
Benet, Carol. Sam Shepard on the German Stage: Critics, Politics, Myths. New York: Peter Lang, 1993.
Wilcox, Leonard, ed. Rereading Shepard: Contemporary Critical Essays on the Plays of Sam Shepard. Basingstoke, Macmillan, 1993.
Wade, Leslie A. Sam Shepard and the American Theater. Westport, Conn.: Greenwood Press, 1997.
Bottoms, Stephen J. The Theater of Sam Shepard: States of Crisis. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1998.
Authors, American -- 20th century; Dramatists; Actors; Motion pictures -- Production and direction; Screenwriters -- United States; Literature; Film; Shepard, Sam, 1943-2017
- Plays, 1982-1999
  Series Description
  The series for Plays is the largest of Shepard's works and includes notes, annotated typescripts, playbills, programs, correspondence, sound recordings, rehearsal schedules, reviews, and publicity. This series is notable in that Shepard meticulously identified each annotated draft with the date and place (by city and state) of each revision, and there tend to be multiple drafts of each work represented.
  - Tooth of Crime (1972)
    - Annotated typescript re-write, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Folder with March 1996 and October 1996 re-writes, December 1996 schedules, contact sheets, reviews, for New York Production. Includes photograph of Mohammed Ali (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence regarding Tooth of Crime, including: correspondence from Signature Theater, 2 audiocassettes of T. Bone Burnett music, and contract for Burnett's musical score (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Review, New York Times, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Sad Lament of Pecos Bill on the Eve of Killing His Wife (1976)
    - Manuscript musical score by Loren Toolajian [housed in box 26], 1997 (Box 1, Folder 5, Box 26)
    - Audiocassette recording of Pecos Bill, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Reviews, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Advertisement (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Curse of the Starving Class (1977)
    - Press kit, including: credits, potential cast, synopsis, biographies, and letters of support (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Reviews, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Buried Child (1977)
    - Published script with Steppenwolf/Chicago re-write annotations (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Final Steppenwolf re-write, annotated typescript, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Re-write, annotated typescript, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Production calendar and correspondence, Brooks Atkinson Theater New York, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Playbills (2), Brooks Atkinson Theater, New York, April-May, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, includes: telegram from Bob Dylan, correspondence with agent Judy Boals, and American Theater magazine regarding publication of Buried Child, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Reviews, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
    - Steppenwolf Chicago Poster, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - True West (1980)
    - Correspondence regarding film rights, 1983-1985 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Repertory Theater of St. Louis program, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Program for Dutch production, February 1984 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Playbill from Le Theatre National de Belgique signed by Shepard, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Program for Ojai, California production, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Posters for French (2) and Turkish (1) productions - FRAMED (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Scripts for New York City radio spots (2), 1983 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Reviews, 1983-1984, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Fool For Love (1983)
    - Bound annotated typescript with cover featuring Elvis kissing a blonde woman. Signed by Shepard, October 1982 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Stage Notes for Magic Theater, handwritten orange notebook, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1983-1985 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - United States reviews, 1983-1996 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Japanese production documents, including: Circle Repertory Company tour program, Tsurumi Shoten publication of script, and bilingual program for KSK Hall production (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Brazilian reviews, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Australian reviews and publicity, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - French program, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Czech publicity materials (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - British (London) reviews, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - A Lie of the Mind (1985)
    - Correspondence, 1985-1992 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Programs (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - CD and audiocassette musical recording by Red Clay Ramblers (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Audiocassette musical recording by Token Oldies (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Reviews, 1985-1993 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Latvian translation by Karina Petrsone, hardbound, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - The War in Heaven (1985)
    - Annotated work play, February 1984 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Audiocassette tapes of rehearsals (2), 1984, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - American Place Theater annotated re-write, February 13, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - American Place Theater re-write with music percussion notes, February 13, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - American Place Theater annotated re-write, February 1991 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - American Place Theater re-write, heavily annotated cover page, February 13, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Programs, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - News clippings, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence with Joseph Chaikin regarding The War in Heaven, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Photocopy of the poem, "What Is the Word," by Samuel Beckett, last Beckett poem to Chaikin (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Sacred Ground (1989)
    - Partial manuscript, 100 handwritten pages in blue spiral notebook includes set drawings, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Sangre de Cristo (unfinished) (1989)
    - Original manuscript bound in spiral notebook, August 25, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Annotated unfinished typescript, November 1989 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - States of Shock (1991)
    - Partial manuscript and annotated typescript titled States of Panic, crossed out titles include Lost Partners, A Fear of Unknown Origin, and The Man Who Couldn't Stop Weeping, November 12, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Notes and dialog, January 1989 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Manuscript and typescript pages for early draft titled Chattanooga, Fanatics, and, Chattanooga Breakdown, January-May 1989 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Annotated typescript subtitled Friendly Fire (2), January 1991 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Second draft, annotated typescript, March 1991 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Stage set drawing sand letter from Bill Stabilie, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Folder containing final draft (March 1991) and re-writes, April4, 1991 and May 5, 1991. Heavily annotated typescript with music and sound cues, and rehearsal schedule for American Place Theater production (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Final script of American Place Theater production, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Final draft, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Sample pages of proposed publication (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Dramatists Play Service publication, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Playbill from American Place Theater production, April 1994 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Reviews, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence from 7 Stages director Faye Allen and from lighting designer Ann Millitello regarding the death of a friend named John Dodd, 1991, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Simpatico (1993)
    - First draft, annotated typescript subtitled Life in the Wake, September 20, 1992-July 13, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Re-writes, September 1992, July 1993, June 1994 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Typescript draft with minimal annotations, July 1993 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Final draft/working rehearsal script with minimal annotations for Public Theater, September 1992-August 1994 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Annotated typescript, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Working script for Joseph Papp Public Theater production, November 1994 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Final corrected version, November 1994 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Notebook with rehearsal notes, rehearsal schedule, correspondence, Fall 1994 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Final Version, April 1998 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Playbill and publicity from Queensland Theater production, April 1996 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Trade book cover art sample (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Reviews, 1993-1995 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Reviews, 1996-1998 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Seduced (1995)
    - Play program from New York production: Kraine Theater, and correspondence (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - The Unseen Hand and Other Plays (1996)
    - Page proofs with annotations and typesetting marks (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - When the World Was Green (1996)
    - Annotated typescript, December 1994 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Annotated typescript, September 1994-August 1995 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Typescript, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Folder for Chicago production includes: correspondence, contact sheets, rehearsal schedules, and heavily annotated working scripts (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Reviews and play program for Atlanta production, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Reviews and play program for San Francisco production, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Reviews and play program for Boston production, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence from Judy Boals, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence with Joseph Chaikin, 1994-1995 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Press release for Gradiva Best Play Award, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Eyes for Consuela (1998)
    - First draft, annotated typescript, October 31,1996 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Working draft, annotated typescript, September 1997 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Folder for Austin production: working script, rehearsal schedules, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Playbill for Manhattan Theater Club production, January 1998 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Reviews, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Unfinished Unidentified Play (1990)
    - Heavily annotated typescript, dates and places include: November 1990, Virginia, December 1990, Florida, and December 1990, Virginia. Character names include: Reeves, Raynelle, Parnell, Clayton, and Joelie. 78 pages total, 1990, undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Annotated typescript, characters include Clayton, Mitch, and Kaylee, undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Unpublished Novels, 1991, undated
  Two annotated typescripts of Stray Hand(working title Slow Dawning of a Sudden Loss), 1991.
  - Stray Hand / Slow Dawning of a Sudden Loss, 1991-1993
    - Annotated typescript, 256 pages with 13 additional pages of re-writes at end titled "Stray Hand", undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Annotated typescript (2 copies) titled "Slow Dawning of a Sudden Loss", 1991-1993 (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
- Short Stories, 1989-1998
  Many of the short stories represented in this series were published in short story compilations Motel Chronicles(1982) and Cruising Paradise(1996). The series has been arranged by those compilation titles. Volador was a working title for Cruising Paradise; those files immediately precede the files labeled Cruising Paradise. The files for Volador / Cruising Paradise include multiple drafts of stories, correspondence, while files for Motel Chronicles include annotated typescripts and production information, but no multiple drafts
  - Motel Chronicles (1982)
    - Signed bound annotated typescript, 1992 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Program for Paris production, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Volador/Cruising Paradise (1989-1998)
    - Spiral bound handwritten draft of Volador includes notes, story drafts, clippings, and photographs. Subjects and titles include: Train Film outline, Chain Chain Chain, Wayne Grace, Madagascar, Phone Call, "Apart," Chappy, Rich Hole, Papantle, Spencer Tracy Had the Right Idea, Nightmare, How I Came by Train, Blythe, Paris, Train to Munich, and Athens, 1989-1991 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Drafts of stories and letter from LuAnn Walther at Random House Publishers inviting Shepard to submit a collection of short stories for publication (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Draft of stories titled Volador and letter to LuAnn Walther at Random House Publishers, June 13, 1989 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Draft of stories titled Volador and letter to LuAnn Walther at Random House Publishers. Story titles include: "The Real Gabby Hayes, Nuevo Mundo, Cruising Paradise, Wild to the Wild, A Small Circle of Friends, Thin Skin, Lily and the Judge, More Urgent Emergencies, The Devouring Lion, Falling Without End, Homage to Celine, Gary Cooper on the Landscape, The Self-Made Man, Hail from Nowhere, Synthetic Pink, Temporary Entrance, Papantla, See You In My Dreams (1 original, 1 photocopy), [1989] undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Draft titled with photocopied photographs. Also titled "Slave of the Camera (an actor's notes)", July 1990 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Volador reading typescript, October 6, 1995 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Annotated typescript (Box 12, Folder 1-4)
    - Page proofs, 1995 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Typescript with typesetting marks, undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Uncorrected proof of Knopf publication, 1996 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Dust jackets for Knopf publication, undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Cover art proposals, undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Unbound Knopf signatures, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Knopf catalog featuring Cruising Paradise, Spring 1996 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Audio book cover art proposals, undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Publicity, 1996 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Reviews, 1996 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence regarding reviews, rights to publish excerpts, and foreign editions, 1996-1998 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Cover art proposals for foreign publications: Minerva, U.K. and La Font, France, 1997 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - The Fire in Jeremy's Lap, undated
    - Annotated and signed typescript, 2 pages, undated (Box 14, Folder 6)
- Films, 1982-1998